Guide to the Vita Sackville-West Papers Relating to Violet Trefusis
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Vita Sackville-West papers relating to Violet Trefusis
1905-1926
GEN MSS 428
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
2.4
(7 boxes)
Collection contains correspondence, writings and additional materials. Correspondence includes letters written by Violet Trefusis to Vita Sackville-West during the 1910's and 1920's concerning their relationship, Trefusis's feelings towards Sackville-West, and the affair's effects on Trefusis's relationship with her husband, Denys Trefusis, her relationship with her mother, Alice Keppel, and Sackville-West's relationship with her husband, Harold Nicolson. Also included are letters by Trefusis to her friend Pat Dansey, and letters from Pat Dansey to Vita Sackville-West. Writings consist of poems and other writings by Trefusis and Sackville-West, and a diary by Trefusis dated May 1905. Additional materials contain two photographs of Vita Sackville-West and a metal bullet of unknown origin.
Sackville-West, V. (Victoria), 1892-1962
Scope and Contents
The Vita Sackville-West Papers Relating to Violet Trefusis document the relationship between Violet Trefusis and Vita Sackville-West. The Papers contain correspondence, writings, photographs and other materials, and have been arranged into three series: Correspondence, Writings, and Additional Materials.
Series I, Correspondence (1910-1925), consists primarily of letters from Violet Trefusis to Vita Sackville-West written during the 1910's and 1920's. The letters illustrate the intensity of Trefusis's involvement in the affair, and describe their time together, their attempts at "escape" or elopement, and the effect of the relationship on Trefusis's life, her marriage to Denys Trefusis, her relationship with her mother, Alice Keppel, and Sackville-West's relationship with her husband, Harold Nicolson. Many of these letters have been published in Violet to Vita: The Letters of Violet Trefusis to Vita Sackville-West, 1910-21, edited by Mitchell A. Leaska and John Phillips (London: Methuen, 1989). Also included in this series are letters from Trefusis to her friend Pat Dansey, letters to Trefusis from Dansey and others, and many letters from Dansey to Vita Sackville-West regarding Trefusis's and Sackville-West's relationship.
Series II, Writings (1905-1921), contains holograph poems and other unidentified writings written by Trefusis and Sackville-West, and one diary kept by Trefusis in May of 1905.
Series III, Additional Materials (1926), contains two photographs of Vita Sackville-West, and a metal bullet of unknown origin.
VITA SACKVILLE-WEST (1892-1962) AND VIOLET TREFUSIS (1894-1972)
Vita Sackville-West and Violet Trefusis (née Keppel) met at a party in the winter of 1905, when Violet was ten and Vita twelve. From the beginning, their relationship was intense, and the constant travels of both families created the necessity of an ongoing and voluminous correspondence (Vita's early letters to Violet were burned by Violet's husband, Denys Trefusis, on their honeymoon).
The friendship became a love affair in 1918, well after Vita's marriage to Harold Nicolson in 1913. Violet herself married Major Denys Trefusis in 1919. Throughout the years 1918 to 1921, the correspondence continued. Violet, who was unhappy in her marriage, often begged Vita to run away with her. They did "elope" briefly to Paris in 1920, but Vita, whose marriage was a happy one, allowed herself to be "rescued" by her husband.
After another trip abroad with Violet in January 1921, Vita chose life with her husband and two sons over life with Violet. Denys Trefusis agreed not to divorce Violet, and she eventually went to live with him in Paris. Violet was forbidden to have any contact with Vita, although letters were exchanged through their mutual confidant, Pat Dansey (who herself became one of Vita's lovers). Slowly, the correspondence came to an end, and aside from a brief meeting at a party in 1924, the two women did not see each other again until 1940, when Violet fled France for England during World War II.
For more detailed biographical information about Violet Trefusis, see the register for the Violet Trefusis Papers (GEN MSS 427).
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Box 7: Restricted fragile material. Reference surrogates have been substituted in the main files. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of and purchased from Nigel Nicolson, 1982 and 1986.
Authors, English -- 20th Century; Lesbian authors; Lesbians; Authors; Dansey, Pat; Keppel, Alice, 1869-1947; Nicolson, Harold, 1886-1968; Sackville-West, V. (Victoria), 1892-1962; Trefusis, Denys; Trefusis, Violet, 1894-1972
- Correspondence, 1910-1925; Series I; 2.1; (5 boxes)
  - VIOLET TREFUSIS CORRESPONDENCE
    - Letters from Violet Trefusis
      Scope and Contents
      To Vita Sackville-West
      - Letters, 1910-18 (Box 1, Folder 1-20)
        Includes: letter from Sidney Russell Cooke to VT, 8 November 1918
      - Letters, [1918?] (Box 2, Folder 21-23)
      - Letters, 1919 (Box 2, Folder 24-39)
      - Letters, [1919?] (Box 3, Folder 40-46)
      - Letters, 1920 Jan-Apr (Box 3, Folder 47-57)
        Includes: Note from Denys Trefusis to VT [February 1920?], which VT sent to VSW
      - Letters, 1920 May-Oct (Box 4, Folder 58-75)
      - Letters, 1920 Nov-Dec (Box 5, Folder 76-81)
      - Letters, 1921-24 (Box 5, Folder 82-84)
      - To Others
        - Dansey, Pat, 1921 (Box 5, Folder 85-86)
    - Letters to Violet Trefusis
      - Dansey, Pat, [1920?] Mar 15 (Box 5, Folder 87)
      - Whitworth, Maurice, 1919 (Box 5, Folder 88)
      - Telegram from unidentified [possibly VSW?], 1920 Mar 11 (Box 5, Folder 89)
  - THIRD PARTY CORRESPONDENCE
    - Dansey, Pat to Vita Sackville-West, 1918-25 (Box 5, Folder 90-91)
    - Sackville-West, Vita to unidentified, [n.y.] Nov 4 (Box 5, Folder 92)
- Writings, 1905-1921; Series II; 0.1; (.5 box)
  - WRITINGS BY VIOLET TREFUSIS
    - "Chapter 7," holograph in VT's hand, [1921 Jul?] (Box 6, Folder 93)
    - Diary, 1905 May (Box 6, Folder 94)
    - Unidentified typescript [by VT?], [1921 May 2] (Box 6, Folder 95)
    - Unidentified typescript [by VT?], n.d. (Box 6, Folder 96)
  - WRITINGS BY VITA SACKVILE-WEST
    - "Carcassonne," holograph poem in VSW's hand (Box 6, Folder 97)
    - Unidentified holograph poem [Sonnet by Alice Meynell?], in VSW's hand, [1920 Feb?] (Box 6, Folder 98)
    - Unidentified holograph in VSW's hand, 1919 Jun 12 (Box 6, Folder 99)
- Additional Material, 1926; Series III; 0.1; (.5 box)
  - PHOTOGRAPHS
    - 2 photographs of VSW, ca. 1926, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 100)
  - OTHER
    - Metal bullet, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 101)
- Restricted Fragile, 0.1; (1 box)
  Restricted Fragile materials may only be consulted with permission of the appropriate curator. Photographic prints for reference use have been substituted in the main files
  - Box 6, folder 101 (Box 7, Folder 102)
    Conditions Governing Access
    Restricted fragile material. Reference surrogates have been substituted in the main files. For further information consult the appropriate curator.